[Pursuit of Jade]
[逐玉]
[Episode 12]
[第12話]
[Yixiang Restaurant]
[溢香楼]
Madam Chen!
陳様
You are late.
遅かったわね
You must drink a penalty drink later.
後で一杯飲んでもらうわよ
Madam Chen.
陳様
Madam Liu!
劉夫人
Look at Madam Song's outfit today.
見て 今日の宋夫人の装い
She's looking more and more noble.
ますます気品にあふれてるわ
I'm flattered, Madam Liu.
劉夫人 褒めすぎるわ
It is my honor to be invited
今日 みんなに招いてもらったことこそ
by you ladies today.
私の光栄だわ
It's an imperial green jade bracelet!
最高級の翡翠の腕輪ね
This is truly hard to come by.
これは本当に手に入らない代物よ
Look at the transparency
この艶と
and the color.
色合い
It must be worth a lot.
きっと高価でしょうね
Let's talk while we walk.
歩きながら話しましょう
Come on.
歩きながら
Let's go.
行きましょう
This bracelet is
この腕輪は
a greeting gift from the Magistrate's wife.
県令夫人がくださった挨拶の品なの
No wonder! So it was a gift from your in-law.
なるほど 義理のお母様からなのね
Yes.
ええ
-Oh, my. -My apologies.
- あら - 失礼しました
You wretched girl!
この小娘
You... Why are you here?
なんでこんなところにいるの
You didn't follow me here just to cause trouble, did you?
わざとついてきて 邪魔しに来たんでしょ？
What? Did you buy this building?
この店をあなたが買ったの？
If you can come, why can't I?
私が来てはいけないわけ？
Do you know each other?
知り合いなの？
No. Who would know her?
彼女なんて知るものか
Madam Liu, let me tell you something.
劉夫人 聞いて
My son's marriage was
息子の縁談は
entirely arranged by the Magistrate.
すべて県知事に手配してくださるの
The Magistrate is from a scholarly family.
県知事は代々学者の家柄で
-Come often if you like it. -He values
- 気に入ったら またどうぞ - 人柄と教養を
character and upbringing.
重んじているの
The betrothal gifts followed ancient customs.
結納品は昔ながらのしきたりで
But my daughter-in-law brought a generous dowry.
むしろ 嫁入り道具のほうが豪華でしたわ
Marriage is
縁組みというのは
all about matching social status.
家柄が 釣り合っていることが肝心なのよ
If the character and upbringing are poor,
人柄も教養もないような相手とは
such a marriage
縁談なんて
-shall never take place. -Indeed.
- 絶対に無理なの - そうね
Right?
そうでしょう
The Magistrate is truly generous.
県令様はずいぶん気前がいいのね
Congratulations
おめでとう
on selling your Scholar Song for a good price.
ご自宅の宋挙人を 高く売りつけたのね
You...
あんた
Well...
この
Wretched girl!
小娘
Let's go inside quickly.
さっさと中に入りましょう
Don't let such a vulgar person
こんな下品な者に
ruin our mood.
気分を害されたくないわ
Right? Come on in.
そうでしょう さあ
What is she talking about?
あの子が言ったのは？
Just nonsense. Forget about it.
でたらめを言っているのよ
Here's a toast to you both.
お二人様に
Manager Yu, you are very experienced
俞店主は客あしらいがお上手で
in receiving guests.
なかなかのやり手だ
It seems you have indeed met a lot of people.
確かに顔が広いようだ
Our restaurant welcomes guests from everywhere.
当店には様々な お客様がいらっしゃいますので
We believe harmony brings wealth.
和気をもつこそ 財が集まることを 重んじてます
In business,
商売ですから
it's always good to know more people.
顔が広いほうが都合がいいものです
Please make yourselves at home, sirs.
では お二人様  ごゆっくり
I need to go attend to other guests now.
私は他のお客様の応対をいたします
Manager, what's wrong?
店主 どうしました？
You look pale.
顔色が悪いですよ
The man in there just touched me.
さっき あの方に触られたの
I don't know why, but that single touch
ちょっと触れただけなのに
gave me the creeps.
体中がぞっとしたのよ
Another guest who tried to grope you?
またいやらしいお客様ですね
How shameless.
本当に恥知らずです
It's not really about groping.
そういうわけでもないの
I feel like I've seen him somewhere before.
どこかで会った気がするのよ
Who was that young lady we met at the door just now?
さっき入り口にいた娘は誰なの？
She is called Fan Changyu.
彼女は樊長玉っていうの
She's a famous disaster from my hometown, Xigu Lane.
以前西固巷で 有名な災いの種だったのよ
The fortune tellers all say
占い師にも言われてたわ
she is a rare jinx seen only once in a millennium.
すごく生涯孤独な運命だって
She not only caused her parents' deaths,
両親を亡くしただけじゃなく
but her uncle was also killed because of her.
伯父さんまで亡くしちゃった
It even went to court!
裁判にまでなったのよ
By the way,
あっ そうだ
just in the middle of this month,
今月の中旬には
a group of bandits broke into her home at night,
夜中に山賊が家に入って
having killed so many people!
たくさんの人が殺されたの
Everyone in Lin'an knows about this.
林安のみんなが知ってるわ
I wonder
あの女の手は
how many people have touched her hands
どれほどの男に触れられたことか
for her to stay so composed
だからこそ平然として
and feel no shame at all.
慎みのかけらもない
I've searched everywhere all these years, yet I failed to find her.
余が長年 探し続けたが見つからなかった
I didn't expect her to be doing so well in Lin'an,
まさか彼女が 林安でうまくやっており
and to have met so many men.
多くの男と知り合っていたなんて
Perhaps it's just her business dealings.
商売上の付き合いかもしれません
You are still making excuses for her.
まだ彼女をかばうか
I dare not.
恐れ多いです
Back then, she left false clues about her fleeing beyond the pass,
昔 彼女が関外へ 逃げたと偽りの情報を残したせいで
causing me to search for her in vain for 6 years.
余は六年間も無駄に探し回った
Never thought she'd establish herself in just 6 years
たった六年で足場を固め
and open such a large restaurant.
こんなに大きな料理店を開くなんて
This woman is really something.
あの女はただ者ではないな
Understood.
かしこまりました
I will go investigate her connections immediately.
すぐに彼女の人脈を調べます
Also, investigate the men around her.
同時に周りの男たちも調べろ
For anyone who has touched her,
彼女に触れた者は
chop off the parts they touched her with,
触れた部位を切り落とし
and present them to me.
余の前に差し出せ
Yes.
はい
I will give the orders right away.
すぐに手配いたします
Why would Manager Yu hire someone like that?
俞店主はなぜ あんな人を雇うのかしら
In the restaurant business,
料理店の商売は
nothing's worse than bad luck.
縁起が悪いのが一番嫌なのに
Perhaps Manager Yu
きっと俞店主は
doesn't know this girl's background,
あの娘の素性を知らずに
so she let a jinx in.
疫病神を店に入れてしまったのね
Madams.
夫人の皆様
Manager Yu.
俞店主
What "jinx"?
疫病神ですって？
We don't have such a dish at Yixiang Restaurant.
うちにそんな料理はないよ
Manager Yu,
俞店主
we are only looking out for your best interests.
私たちは あなたのためを思っているのよ
This jinx
疫病神ってね
can bring death to people.
人を不幸にするのよ
Really?
本当なの？
But I heard
でも私が聞いた話では
that she supported a scholar fiancé for years.
彼女は書生の婚約者を 長年支えていたのに
Once the scholar passed the provincial exam,
相手が挙人に受かった途端
he betrayed her and broke off the engagement.
一方的に婚約を破棄されたそうよ
In my point of view,
私に言わせれば
the mother and son are the real ingrates
あの母子こそ恩知らずで
and jinxes.
大疫病神だわ
They not only harmed the young girl
あの娘を傷つけただけでなく
but also her parents.
その両親までも陥れたんだから
So this talk of a jinx
じゃあ 疫病神の話は
might just be a false rumor.
もしかして噂なのかしら
You're right, Madam Liu.
劉夫人の言う通り
Mrs. Fan
樊姉さんは
not only takes care of her sister all by herself.
妹の面倒を見ながら
Since she joined our Yixiang Restaurant,
うちの溢香楼に来てくれてから
my braised meat business
この煮込み肉の商売が
has been booming.
どんどん繁盛してるのよ
I think
私に言わせれば
she's actually an auspicious blessing!
あの子は福の神なの
However, Madam Song,
ところで宋夫人
who told you she was a jinx?
彼女が疫病神だって誰から聞いたの
Just some gossip, I suppose.
人から聞いた話よ
Why do women
女なのに
have to make things hard for other women?
どうして傷つけ合うの
Spouting nonsense and gossiping all day
四六時中 でたらめや陰口ばかりで
will bring about God's punishment.
天罰が下るよ
As educated and reasonable as you are, Madam Song,
宋夫人は教養のある方だし
how could you gossip like some filthy trash?
下品な人のように 陰口なんて言わないでしょ
You must have been deceived.
きっと誰かに騙されたの
Why are there still some dishes not served?
料理がまだ揃わないの？
I'll go check on them.
催促してくるわ
Madams, please enjoy the food.
夫人の皆様 ごゆっくり
Okay.
ええ
You know what?
知らないでしょう？
This manager
ここの店主も
got pregnant out of wedlock.
婚前に妊娠したのよ
Who knows whose bastard
このお腹の子は
she carried in her belly?
誰のかも分からないわ
"Why do women have to make things hard for other women?" Ridiculous.
女の敵は女って
I think she's obviously
どう見ても
an immoral slut
樊長玉と同じ
just like Fan Changyu.
婦道に悖る卑しい女よ
Let's
私たちは
not let other people's gossip
他人の揉め事で
ruin our mood.
興醒めするのはやめよう
Yes, exactly.
そうね
Let's get back to the point.
本題に戻りましょう
A bunch of noisy gossips.
うるさいおしゃべり女共
According to them,
あの女の話では
the child might be hiding in this restaurant.
あの子供は 店の中にいるかもしれません
The one who talks the most,
一番喋りな女に
teach her a lesson.
少し灸を据えてやれ
Understood.
はい
-Madam Liu. -Do you think I'm drunk?
- 劉夫人 - 酔ってると思ってるの？
You drank too much.
酔ったわ
For this matter, please put in a good word for me
この件は義理のお父様の前で
-in front of your son's father-in-law. -Don't worry. Just leave it to me.
- よく言っていただけますよう - 安心して 私に任せて
"Bring about God's punishment"?
天罰が下るだなんて
I think the one to suffer God's punishment
本当に天罰が下るなら
s-should be that wretched girl!
あの娘が先よ
If God
天に
really sees us all,
本当に目があるなら
He should make that wretched girl...
あの娘を…
You'd better think twice before you speak nonsense
口を利く前に考えろ
and watch your mouth.
その臭い口を閉じろ
If you spout nonsense again,
次にでたらめを言ったら
it won't end as easily as today.
今日のように簡単には済まないぞ
O-Okay.
はい
I-I get it.
わ… 分かりました
Madam.
夫人
[Braised pork tongue]
[豚舌の煮込み]
[Braised pork belly]
[ばら肉の煮込み]
[Fan's Braised Meat Shop]
[樊記煮込み屋]
Are there any pig ears left?
豚の耳はまだあるの？
None left today.
今日はもう売り切れました
You may come again tomorrow.
また明日お越しください
It's almost New Year.
もうすぐ年越しね
Our braised meat is
うちの煮込み肉も
selling better and better.
どんどん売れるようになって
You've worked really hard.
本当にご苦労さま
You're the one working hard,
あなたこそ大変よ
busy with so many things every day.
毎日こんなに忙しいのに
Making money is never easy.
稼ぐのは楽じゃないわ
However,
でも
although our braised meat is selling well,
うちの煮込み肉は 売れ行きがいいけど
if we want to take it to the next level,
今後さらに上を目指すなら
we could design an emblem for our braised meat.
自分の煮込み肉の図案を 作るといいわ
An emblem?
図案？
But my braised meat is either sliced and served on a plate,
でもうちの煮込み肉は 切って皿に盛るか
or wrapped in oil paper for takeout.
油紙に包んで持ち帰るだけよ
What's the use of an emblem?
図案なんて何に使うの？
It's exceptionally useful.
すごく役に立つわ
Come out here.
外に来て
[Fan's Braised Meat Shop]
[[樊記煮込み屋]
Look
見て
at these shops downstairs from mine.
階下の店を
Fang's tea,
方家の茶屋や
Li's wine.
李家の酒屋
[Luo's Pawnshop]
[羅氏質屋]
Doesn't every shop have an emblem?
どの店にも図案があるでしょ
[Fang's Tea Shop]
[方家茶屋]
[Fang]
[方]
And each one is unique.
しかも全部違っていて
[Li]
[李]
[Hua San]
[花三]
You can tell whose shop it is at a glance.
一目でどこの店か分かる
Later, think of a design for your emblem.
後で図案の形を考えて
You can make a banner to hang by the signboard,
布にして看板の横に掛ければ
so people can see it from afar.
遠くからでも見えるわ
And make some more oil paper.
それから油紙も用意して
Print the emblem on the oil paper, too.
油紙にも図案の印を捺すのよ
When someone buys braised meat,
客が煮込み肉を買いに来たら
wrap it in that oil paper.
その油紙で包むの
Your fame will surely surpass the Wang's.
そうすれば きっと王記よりも有名になるわ
I got it.
いいよ
I'll find you
私が字の上手な
a scholar with nice handwriting.
秀才を探してくるわ
Let's get this done today.
今日中に済ませましょう
Qianqian.
浅姉さん
[Fan's Braised Meat Shop]
[樊記煮込み屋]
My husband can write as well.
うちの旦那さんも字が上手なの
I'll just ask him to help.
私が頼めばいいの
How is your husband's handwriting?
旦那さんの字はどうなの？
Excellent.
すごく上手なの
Really.
本当よ
Even more beautiful than his face.
彼の顔よりも字のほうが素敵なの
That impressive?
そんなに上手なの？
Then he must be as great as the legendary calligraphers,
じゃあ 王羲之や (王羲之：中国で一番有名な書道家です)
Wang Xizhi and Zhong Yao!
鍾繇の再世よ (鍾繇:王羲之より昔のすごく偉い書道家です)
Wang Xi...
王羲…
I don't know who those two are,
その二人のことは知らないけど
but I think he's about that good.
たぶん同じくらいと思う
Changyu,
長玉
I really love
あなたの性格は
your personality.
本当に気に入ったわ
[Fan]
[樊]
Sir, your handwriting is truly elegant.
若様の字は本当に見事だな
-Yes. -Having worked here for years,
- そうね - 俺の店で長年やってきたが
I've never seen anyone's handwriting
こんなに上手い字は
as good as yours, sir.
今まで見たことがない
Truly amazing.
本当に上手
-It's so well written. -Manager, look.
- すごく上手だ - 店主 見てください
[Fan]
[樊]
It's so beautiful.
すごくきれいに書けたね
Do you want to take a break?
ちょっと休んだら？
No need. I'll keep writing.
大丈夫だ 続けろ
Changyu.
長玉
Your husband's handwriting...
あなたの旦那さんの字
It's really good!
本当に上手ね
Much better than that Wang...
あの王…
Wang something.
王なんとかよりずっと上手よ
Fine. Beauty is in the eye of the beholder.
わかった 惚れた欲目ってやつね
Of course it's good.
悪く見えるわけないわ
Yes. No matter what Zheng writes or draws,
そうよ 義兄さんが 書いたもの描いたものは
I think it's the best.
私にはすべて素敵に見えるのよ
Fuling, take Changning upstairs to have some goodies.
茯苓 寧娘を連れて上へ行って
You can eat whatever you want.
好きなものを何でも食べて
Thank you, Fairy Sister.
優しい姉ちゃん ありがとう
That's so sweet.
口が甘いわね
Off you go.
さあ
Changyu,
長玉
you really found yourself
本当に
a husband good with both brains and brawn.
文武両道のいい夫を見つけたわね
Thank you for the compliment.
ありがとう
No need to thank me.
何を礼を言うの
From today on,
今日からは
we must stick together.
一緒に頑張って
Show those gossips
陰口を叩く人たちに 見せつけましょう
that we young women are also capable of great deeds!
女でも大業を成せるって
[Fan]
[樊]
-I want some, too! -I also want some!
私も 私も
[Fan's Braised Meat Shop]
[[樊記煮込み屋]
Me too! I want one!
こっちも欲しい
[Fan]
[樊]
Qianqian, you're so insightful.
浅姉さん すごいだね
You said drawing these things
これを描けば
would attract a lot of people, and it really did!
本当にこんなに 人が引きつけられるのね
You're mistaken.
勘違いしてるわ
The real attraction is
人を引きつけているのは
your husband.
あなたの旦那さんよ
[Fan's Braised Meat Shop]
[[樊記煮込み屋]
Why are you still standing there?
ぼっとしないで
Go help him.
早く手伝って
Go, go, go.
ほら 早く
I'll help you.
手伝うわ
Here you are.
どうぞ
Isn't this the meat you wanted?
注文した肉じゃないですか
This was just wrapped up.
これがさっき包んだものだ
Yes.
うん
Is what he takes different?
彼が持ってるのと違うの？
Yes, the meat he hands over smells better.
彼がくれた肉の方が美味しいの
-I want some, too! -I also want some!
私も 私も
Give it to me! Me!
ちょうだい
That's mine! Give it to me! I want some, too!
これは私の 私も欲しい
Here you are.
はい
You can do it.
頑張って
It's fine. It's okay.
大丈夫よ
You weighed this wrong.
間違ってるわよ
No rush, sir.
若様 急がなくていい
No need to rush.
急がなくていいよ
It's underweight.
足りなかったから
I cut an extra piece.
多めに切っておいた
Here you are.
さあ
What does it have to do with you?
あなたとは関係ないでしょ
Stay out of this.
余計なお世話よ
-I want some, too! -I also want some!
私も 私も
-Me, too. -Any meat left?
- 私も - まだあるの？
I shouldn't have let you come.
こんななら来なきゃよかった
-Give it to me. I'll pay double the price. -I also want some!
- これをちょうだい  倍払うよ - 私も
[Fan's Braised Meat Shop]
[[樊記煮込み屋]
Is there any left?
まだあるか
Sorry, sir.
すみません
We're sold out for today.
今日はもう売り切れです
What about those in the back?
後ろのは？
Those are just scraps.
これは切り落としです
Scraps are fine, too.
切り落としでもいい
Are you selling them or not?
売らないのか
Yes. If you pay, I'll sell.
売りますよ 金をいただければ
Here, take it.
さあ 持って
Your hands are greasy.
手に油がついてるから
Be careful not to dirty the paper on top.
上の紙を汚すな
[Fan]
[樊]
This calligraphy is brilliant.
見事な字だな
Using it to wrap meat is
肉を包むのに使うなんて
squandering a treasure.
まさにもったいない
[Fan]
[樊]
Really nice.
いいね
"Squandering a treasure"?
もったいないって
What does that mean?
もったいないってどういう意味？
Let's pack up.
片付けよう
[Welcome guests from far and wide]
[客達九州]
I'm not drunk.
酔ってない
Take care, Mr. Wu.
呉若様 お気をつけて
Qianqian.
浅浅
Go wait for me in the carriage.
馬車で待ってろ
Did you enjoy your drink, Mr. Wu?
呉若様 お楽しみいただけましたか
It's getting late. It's time to go home.
夜も更けました そろそろお帰りくださいませ
Why go home?
帰るなんて
Everyone knows I am
俺がここの常連だって
a regular here.
誰もが知っているだろ
-Mr. Wu. -Let's go.
- 呉若様 - 行こう
Drink a few more cups with me.
もう二杯 付き合ってくれ
I'm doing this for your own good.
若様のためを思ってのことです
If you go back late,
もし遅くお帰りになれば
Mrs. Wu will come cause trouble
呉夫人がまた
for our Yixiang Restaurant again.
うちに文句を言いに来られますよ
Don't use that fierce woman to pressure me.
あの女を盾にするな
Listen carefully.
言っておくが
If you don't keep me good company today,
今日しっかりと 付き合ってもらわなければ
don't expect to keep this place running smoothly.
この小さな店を営業させないぞ
Mr. Wu, please mind your manners.
呉若様 ご自重ください
Go away!
どけ
How dare you, a maid, talk to me like that?
俺に向かってそんな口を聞くとは
-Who taught you to do that? -Mr. Wu!
- 誰が教えたのだ - 呉若様
Mr. Wu.
呉若様
Calm down, please.
まあまあ
I'll drink with you.
私がお相手します
Bring the cups.
杯を持ってきて
Cheers.
飲め
How dare you,
あなたのような悪者が
a scoundrel, run wild here?
ここで好き勝手するなんて
I've dealt with countless men like you.
私は今まで何人も始末してきたのよ
Send him back to the Wu's Mansion
呉府まで送り届けて
and hand him over to Mrs. Wu!
呉夫人に引き渡す
Yes.
はい
Let go!
放せ
Who do you think you are?
何様だと思ってるんだ？
Do you know who I am?
俺が誰だか知らないのか
Bitch!
このクソ女が
Are you alright?
大丈夫か
Here you are, Mr. Qi.
斉若様 どうぞ
Master, what should we do with him?
館様 こいつをどうしますか
Do as Manager Yu said.
俞店主の言う通り
Send him back to Mrs. Wu at the Wu's Mansion.
呉府の呉夫人に引き渡せ
Remember, send him back alive.
生かしておけ
Don't cause trouble for Manager Yu.
俞店主に迷惑をかけるな
-Yes! -Understood.
- はい
Manager Yu, you look pale.
俞店主 顔色が悪いな
Were you frightened just now?
さっき驚いたのか
I'm fine.
大丈夫です
Thank you for saving me, Mr. Qi.
斉若様 お助けいただき感謝します
Farewell.
それでは
Manager, are you okay?
店主 大丈夫ですか
He behaves a bit like that guy,
仕草は少し似ていたけど
but there's no scar on his face.
顔に傷もないし
And the voice is different, too.
声も違う
Don't scare yourself.
気にしすぎだよ
Why would he come to Lin'an?
彼がどうして林安に来るわけ
Who?
誰のことですか
Nothing.
何でもない
[Permeating fragrance]
[香溢千里]
These snacks are all for you.
このお菓子は 全部あなたのために用意したの
My sister can really eat as well.
お姉ちゃんも本当によく食べるの
She eats enough for 3 meals in one sitting,
ご飯なら一度に 三杯も食べるんだから
with her rice bowl as big as a soup tureen.
茶碗は汁椀みたいに大きいの
Your sister is impressive!
お姉さん すごいね
Have you ever seen a pig slaughter?
豚屠りのを見たことあるの？
No.
ない
My sister can knock a pig out
うちのお姉ちゃんは張り手一発で
with one single slap.
豚ちゃんを気絶させられるの
Really?
本当なの？
I've never seen anyone
こんなにすごいお姉さん
as formidable as your sister.
見たがことないわ
Fuling, come over and help!
茯苓 早く手伝いに来て
I'm going out for a bit.
ちょっと出かけて
I'll be right back.
すぐ戻るから
Thief!
泥棒
I... I'm not a thief.
ぼ…僕は泥棒じゃない
I don't care who you are.
誰だろうと関係ない
You are stealing food.
こっそり食べてるんだから
I'm going to tell my sister and the Fairy Sister.
お姉ちゃんと 優しい姉ちゃんに言いつける
Don't!
やめろ
Changyu, someone is stealing food!
お姉ちゃん 誰かこっそり食べてる
It's all because you're stealing food!
誰に許されてこっそり食べてるのよ
This is my home.
ここは僕の家だ
My mother owns this restaurant.
母さんはこの店の店主だ
Why can't I eat it?
食べちゃいけないわけないだろ
You are the Fairy Sister's son?
優しい姉ちゃんの息子なの？
What's your name? How old are you?
名前は？ 今年はいくつなの？
I'm Yu Bao'er. I'm 6.
僕は俞宝児 六歳だよ
What about you?
君は？
Try this piece.
こっちを食べてみて
Just this piece is enough for me.
これで十分だよ
Mother doesn't let me eat too much.
母さんが たくさん食べちゃダメって言うの
She says too many sweets cause cavities.
甘いものを食べ過ぎると 虫歯になるって
What are cavities?
虫歯って何？
They're like...
ええとね
Little worms will eat your teeth.
歯が虫に食べられちゃって
It hurts so much.
すごく痛いんだ
Worms will grow?
虫がつくの？
Like cabbage worms or rice weevils?
青虫みたいなの？それとも米の虫？
I don't know, either.
僕も知らない
I've never had them.
虫歯になったことないから
Then we'd better not eat anymore.
じゃあ 食べないほうがいい
How about we go play outside together?
一緒に遊びに行かない？
Mother says I have a special fate,
母さんが僕は特殊な運命だから
and I should avoid seeing too many people.
あまり人と会わないように言うの
Only then...
そうすれば
Only then can I stay safe.
無事でいられるって
Then let's play hide-and-seek.
じゃあ かくれんぼしよう
You can't take this.
それはだめ
-Kids... -Go away.
- あんた… - 早く行って
-Sorry. -I'm sorry.
- すみません - ごめんね
Bao'er?
宝児
Why are you here?
どうしてここに？
-This way. -Let's go.
- こっちよ - 早く 早く
Your mother told you not to run around!
母に出歩くなと言われただろ
You two. Don't touch it.
二人とも 動かないで
It doesn't matter.
別にいいだろ
-Just a moment. -OK, I'll go back later.
- 少しだけ - じゃあ あとで戻るわ
Where did you come from, brats?
どこのガキが
You spoiled my mood. Get out.
邪魔しやがって 出ていけ
You're still running here?
まだ逃げるか
Stop!
待て
Run!
早く逃げて
You brats, how dare you ruin my day?
このガキ 邪魔しやがって
Get lost!
どけ
Changning?
寧娘
She's not here.
ここにはいないか
I'll go in and light the lamps for you two first.
お二人のために灯をともしましょう
No need to light the lamps in this room.
この部屋は灯をともさなくてよい
Arrange the wine and dishes the same as on our first day here.
酒と料理は来た時と 同じように用意してくれ
Got it.
はい
Keep this in mind.
覚えておけ
No matter when or where,
いつでも
never make decisions on my behalf,
余のために勝手な判断をするな
even if we kill the wrong person.
たとえ人を間違えて殺しても
Do you understand?
分かったか
Yes.
はい
I'm so sleepy.
眠い
Shh. Be quiet.
しーっ 静かに
How is the investigation going?
あの件はどうなったか
I've asked around.
色々と探りを入れました
Based on the time she arrived in Lin'an,
彼女が林安へ 来た年月から推しますと
the child was very likely conceived in the Prince's Mansion.
あの子は王府で 身ごもった可能性が極めて高いです
To confirm her identity with absolute certainty,
十全に身元を確かめるには
we need the Nanny to come to Lin'an to verify it in person.
ばあやに自ら来て 検査していただく必要があります
Then go arrange it now.
なら早く行かせろ
I'll get on it right away.
すぐに手配いたします
Who's there?
誰だ？
Sold out so early?
もう売り切れの？
All sold out for today.
今日はもう売り切れました
Please come again tomorrow.
また明日どうぞ
Okay.
分かった
Make way.
どけ
Mr. Li, where are these soldiers from?
李叔父さん この兵たちはどこから来たの？
Advisor Guo, who freeloaded here yesterday, said
昨日食い逃げしていった郭師爺が
the front lines are in trouble, so they're requisitioning grain again.
前線の食料が足りなくて また食糧を徴収しに来た
Looks like
どうやら
these soldiers are here for the grain.
こいつらは徴収に来た兵士のようだ
Wei Xuan's bound to be defeated.
魏宣が負けるのは 時間の問題だったが
I just didn't expect that he couldn't even hold on until the New Year.
年越しまでもたないとはな
I also heard
それに聞いた話じゃ
that in Chongzhou, in order to collect grain,
崇州では食糧徴収のために
they drove farmers to their deaths.
農民を死に追いやったそうだ
They all say Mr. He in our Jizhou is
我々の霽州の賀奉行様は
a just and upright official.
ご明察なお奉行様だと言われている
I hope he won't be like those in Chongzhou,
崇州のように
just to collect grain,
食糧徴収のために
driving the common people to their deaths.
民を死に 追いやることだけはやめてほしい
It all depends on how the Jizhou Government will handle it.
霽州府のやり方次第だな
What is this for?
何をしている？
It's yours.
あなたの分
I don't need it. You keep it.
いらない しまっておけ
No.
だめ
Half for each of us.
半分こよ
You wrote hundreds of paper packets.
何百枚も書いたんだから
I might lose it if I carry it.
私が持ってると失くしやすい
You keep it for me.
預かっておいてくれ
Fine. I'll keep it for you.
分かったわ 預かっておく
Okay.
よし
Have you seen Changning?
寧娘を見なかった？
She's missing.
姿が見えないの
Those goddamn bandits are after us again?
あの人でなしどもがまた来たの？
-Bao'er! -Changning!
- 宝児 - 寧娘
Bao'er!
宝児
Who is Bao'er?
宝児って誰？
My son.
私の息子よ
Fuling!
茯苓
Manager, Bao'er isn't in the secret room.
店主 宝児が隠し部屋にいません
Changning was just here.
寧娘はさっきまでここにいたのに
I went out for a bit,
ちょっと外に出てる間に
and she's gone.
いなくなってしまったんです
Qi...
斉のやつ
It must be him.
絶対あの斉のやつだ
Who is Qi?
斉のやつって 誰なの？
That man comes every day.
あの人は毎日来るの
Every time I see him,
彼を見ると
I get goosebumps.
いつも鳥肌が立つの
He must be the one who took Bao'er away!
きっと彼が宝児をさらったのよ
Let's split up and search.
手分けして探せ
Okay.
わかった
Has that guest surnamed Qi left?
斉のやつはもう行ったの？
I-I don't know.
し…知りません
Manager, please calm down.
店主 落ち着いてください
Where is that guy surnamed Qi?
斉のやつは？
He just left not long ago.
先ほど出たばかりです
Did he have anyone with him when he left?
誰かを連れてはいなかった？
He left in a hurry.
慌てて出て行かれました
I didn't notice
誰かを連れていたかは
whether he had anyone with him.
見ておりません
-Manager!
- 店主
Calm down, please!
店主 落ち着いてください
Manager, are you alright?
店主 大丈夫ですか
How is your hand?
手はどうですか
Let me see.
見せてください
I'll get on it right away.
すぐに手配いたします
Who's there?
誰だ？
Sir, it's me.
お客様 私です
Sorry, sir.
お客様 申し訳ありません
I accidentally knocked over the lampstand just now.
さっき不注意で 燭台を倒してしまいました
Did I disturb you?
お邪魔いたしませんでした でしょうか
Give it to me.
渡せ
You can go now.
もういい
Enjoy your meal.
ごゆっくり
[Heaven-class]
[天字號]
How have I taught you?
私が普段どう教えているの？
I... I dare not forget, Mother.
わ… 忘れていない 母さん
I was just...
ただ…
Just what?
ただ何なの？
Just playing around?
ただ遊びたかっただけなの？
Do you just let everything
私がいつも言っていることを
I usually tell you go in one ear and out the other?
聞き流しているの
Why won't you listen?
なぜ言うことを聞かないの？
Why are you so playful?
なぜ遊んでばかりいるの？
Qianqian, your hand is hurt.
浅姉さん 手を怪我したの？
Why don't you go apply some medicine?
早く薬を塗ってね
[Heaven-class]
[天字號]
Fairy Sister, please don't be mad.
優しい姉ちゃん 怒らないで
It's my fault. I fell asleep.
全部私が寝ちゃったせいなの
Bao'er was just keeping me company.
宝児も 私に付き合ってくれただけなの
I won't blame you.
あなたのせいじゃないわ
Can I come play with Bao'er again in the future?
じゃあ これからも 宝児に遊びに来てもいい？
Get up now. The ground is cold.
早く立って 床は冷たいわ
Mother.
母さん
[Heaven-class]
[天字號]
Qianqian is usually so nice to everyone.
浅姉さんはいつも 誰にでも丁寧なのに
But why does she treat her own son like an enemy?
どうして息子には 敵みたいに当たるの？
Her reaction today was
彼女の今日の反応は
indeed more fearful than yours.
確かに君よりも少し怖がっていた
I'm going back to check on her.
もう一度彼女を見に戻るね
Even close friends have their secrets.
親友でも言えない秘密はあるものだ
She will tell you when she wants to.
話したくなれば 自分から話してくれる
I wonder what Qianqian has been through.
浅姉さん 一体何があったの
Changyu, I'm sleepy.
お姉ちゃん 眠い
She's sleepy.
彼女は眠たいわ
Come on, Changning.
さあ 寧娘
Hold onto me.
抱きついて
[He]
[賀]
[Peace at the border]
[邊順境安]
In our Great Yin's 1 capital city and 17 prefectures,
大胤国には一京十七府
the Northwest comprises 4 of them.
西北には四つの府がある
Jinzhou is barren, and Chongzhou has rebelled.
瑾州は痩せた土地で 崇州はもう反旗を翻した
That leaves only 2 prefectures, Jizhou and Yanzhou.
残っているのは霽州と焉州だけだ
Yanzhou is
焉州は
a garrison post.
兵が駐屯する地で
The Imperial Court strictly forbids hoarding grain or farming there.
朝廷は兵糧の備蓄と 農作業を固く禁じている
That means right now in the Northwest,
つまり今 西北で
only our Jizhou prefecture can supply grain.
兵糧を供給できるのは 我々の霽州だけだ
Wei Xuan
あの魏宣は
clearly thinks the fire of war in Chongzhou is
崇州の戦火が
not raging enough.
まだ足りないとでも思うのか
Wei Xuan sent troops to requisition grain by force.
魏宣は軍隊を遣わして 強制的に食糧徴収した
The soldiers even took the seeds farmers kept.
農民の穀物の種がまた奪われた
Forget about spring planting of the common people.
民は来年の春まきどころか
[He]
[賀]
It'll already be a blessing for them to just survive the harsh winter.
厳しい冬を越せるかも危うい状況だ
Doing this is
こんなことをすれば
like digging our own grave!
自滅するのと同じだ
Why couldn't we collect enough grain?
なぜ食糧が徴収できないのか
I've had it investigated.
すでに調べさせました
A month ago,
一か月前
a group of merchants from out of town
よその商人たちが
bought up grain everywhere at high prices.
各地で食糧を高値で 買い占めていました
The people only kept seeds and coarse grain for themselves,
民は穀物の種と 自分たちが食べる分だけを残し
and sold all the rest.
あとは 全部売り渡してしまったのです
Buying grain in wartime.
戦を前に食糧を買い占めるか
Go investigate these merchants from out of town.
このよその商人連中を調べ上げよ
-Yes, General.
かしこまりました
Your Lordship, I've figured it out.
侯爺 すべて調べがつきました
The one who bought grain in the city is
城中で食糧を買い占めている者は
the manager of Lin'an Rice Shop,
林安米屋の店主で
named Zhao Xun.
趙詢と申します
He united grain merchants from many places
各地の穀商と手を組み
to buy grain at high prices in Yanzhou and Jizhou,
焉州と霽州で米を高値で買い占め
totaling nearly 200,000 piculs.
その数二十万石に上ります
Zhao Xun?
趙詢？
Has he been closely interacting with someone recently?
最近 誰かと親しくしていたか
Yes, someone who claimed to be a rice merchant from the Capital,
おります 京城から来た米商で
surnamed Qi.
齊と申します
Qi?
斉って？
Mr. Qi,
斉若様
our manager hasn't recovered from her cold yet.
うちの店主は風邪が治っておらず
She has been resting behind closed doors
っと閉じこもって療養しております
and really can't see anyone.
そのためお目にかかれず
Hope you can understand it, sir.
どうかお許しください
If it's a cold,
風邪というのなら
why didn't she accept
なぜ私が名医に
the medicine I had a famous doctor prescribe for her?
処方させた薬を受け取らない
She didn't even accept the fox-fur coat.
狐の毛皮さえ受け取ろうとしない
Is it not warm enough for her?
寒さしのぎには足りないのか
Or is it that
それとも
your manager is avoiding me on purpose?
店主はわざと私を避けているのか
No way.
とんでもございません
Our manager doesn't mean to slight you.
失礼をするつもりなどではなく
She is just seriously ill.
ただ病状が重いだけなのです
How serious?
どれほど病んでいるのだ？
She's not dead yet, is she?
まだ生きているだろう
Tell her,
店主に伝えろ
I always get to see the person I want to see.
私が会いたい人は必ず会わせろ
So it's you, Mr. Qi! Welcome.
あら 斉若様でいらっしゃいました
Go serve the dishes. The best ones.
早く料理を出して 上等なのを
Yes.
はい
Serve the most expensive ones.
上等なのを出して
It seems you're fine.
元気そうじゃないか
It's just a cold.
風邪だけですので
Nothing serious.
大したことございませんわ
Besides, the physician said it's more important to keep inner peace.
医者に心を穏やかにするのが 一番だと聞いております
Don't get angry or sad,
怒ったり 悲しんだり
and avoid looking at disgusting things.
不快なものは見ないほうが
That helps with recovery.
回復によいのです
Don't move.
動くな
Men and women aren't supposed to get intimate.
男女として
Please show some respect, Mr. Qi.
節度を守っていただきたいです
I said, don't move.
動くな
Your pulse was slow just now.
さっきは脈が穏やかで
It's indeed like a chill.
確かに風邪のようだった
But now it has quickened a lot.
だが今はずっと速くなっている
This medicine is exactly what you need.
この薬が君にちょうど合っている
Thank you, Mr. Qi.
斉若様 ありがとうございます
Manager Yu, you seem to dislike me so much.
俞店主は私のことが嫌いなようだ
What are you talking about?
とんでもないです
It's not that I dislike you.
嫌いなどということはございません
It's just that I haven't recovered from my cold,
ただ風邪がまだ 治っていないものですから
and I'm afraid I'll spoil your mood
お食事のお気分を
for enjoying the delicacies.
損ねるのが心配なだけです
I'll take my leave then.
ではこれで失礼いたします
Where are you going?
どこへ？
None of your business.
関係ないでしょ
I wanted you to take the medicine
薬を飲ませるのは
for your own good.
君のためだ
There are plenty of men who care about me.
私を気にかける男なんて たくさんいるわ
Go wait in line.
列に並びなさい
Who are they?
誰だ？
Let go.
放して
Let go of me!
放してよ
What are you doing?
何をするの！
Mr. Qi's concern for Manager Yu is
斉若様の俞店主へのご厚意
truly a grand gesture.
実に気前がいいものだ
He actually booked the entire Yixiang Restaurant.
この溢香楼を貸し切るとは
Manager Yu,
俞店主
now you can have a good rest.
これでゆっくり休めるな
You booked my Yixiang Restaurant?
私の溢香楼を貸し切ったの？
Manager Zhao just said
先ほど趙店主が
he'd offer 100 taels a day
一日一百両で溢香楼を
to book the Yixiang Restaurant for 10 days.
十日間貸し切ると申しました
Ten days.
十日間
I'm booking everything
この溢香楼の全てを
in the Yixiang Restaurant.
私が貸し切った
Only 100 taels a day?
一日たったの百両なんて
Did you not bring enough money?
金が足りなかったの？
At least 1,000 taels a day.
最低でも一日一千両にしなきゃ
Not a wen less.
一文たりとも欠けたら 話にならないわ
Do you have that much?
出せるの？
Just this little?
これだけか
[Yixiang Restaurant]
[溢香楼]
That's strange.
おかしいね
How weird.
おかしいな
The Manager didn't notify us.
店主から何も聞いてないんだ
-Excuse me. -The Restaurant is closed to reorganize.
- すみません - 溢香楼は改装のため 休業いたします
We appreciate your understanding.
皆様のご理解をお願いいたします
[The Restaurant is closed to reorganize. We appreciate your understanding.]
[溢香楼は改装のため 休業いたします 皆様のご理解をお願いいたします]
Why is it closed all of a sudden?
どうして急に休業になったの？
Where is Manager Yu?
俞店主はどこにいるの？
We also came to work early this morning
私たちも朝来て
and just found out.
初めて知ったんだ
We haven't seen Manager Yu.
俞店主には会っていない
This is weird.
おかしいな
Madam Man, Mr. Li.
満婆さん 李叔父さん
Why is the Yixiang Restaurant closed?
どうして溢香楼は閉まったの？
Mr. Qi booked the whole place.
斉という若様に貸し切られて
He sent us back to rest for a few days,
数日休むように言われたの
saying he doesn't need us to serve.
用事もないって
It's weird, though.
それにしてもおかしいな
Even the doors are all locked.
店の戸に鍵までかかってるし
In all my years at the Yixiang Restaurant,
溢香楼で何年も働いてるが
I've never seen this happen before.
こんなことは初めてだ
Indeed.
そうだな
Where is Qianqian?
じゃあ 浅姉さんは？
She was sick yesterday,
昨日は体調が悪かったの
so she must be inside now.
きっと中にいるわ
Yes.
そうだ
I'll go take a look.
見てくる
The doors are locked.
戸に鍵がかかっているのに
You're not actually thinking of flying...
飛んで中に入ろうってのか
She actually flew over.
本当に飛んで行った
Qianqian!
浅姉さん
-Qianqian! -Don't come over!
- 浅姉さん - 来ないで
Help!
助けて
Don't come over. Stay back.
来ないで
-Qianqian. -No...
- 浅姉さん - やめて
No.
やめて
-No! -Qianqian.
- 嫌だ - 浅姉さん
Get lost!
どいて
-Go away!
- どいて
No!
やめて
Changyu...
長玉
It's okay.
もう大丈夫よ
What's wrong?
どうしたの？
What dream did you have
どんな夢を見たの
to scare you so much?
そんなに怖がって
I dreamed of a madman.
狂人の夢を見たの
Go away!
どいて
A masked madman.
仮面をつけた狂人よ
Here you are.
ほら
Madam Man said the Yixiang Restaurant was
満婆さんが溢香楼は
booked by Mr. Qi.
斉という若様に 貸し切られたって言ってたの
What's going on?
どういうことなの？
No.
そんなことないよ
I didn't dare take on this business.
こんな商売は無理
Why?
どうしたの？
I deliberately asked for 1,000 taels,
わざと一千両を要求したのに
but he still agreed.
彼はあっさり承知したの
The more I thought about it, the more scared I got.
考えれば考えるほど怖くなって
So I just closed up the restaurant to avoid him.
いっそ店を閉めて 隠れることにしたの
Is it possible
もしかして
that he just likes you?
あなたのことが好きなだけなのかも
I don't know.
私も分からないの
I just feel like
このことはどうもそんなに
it's not that simple.
単純じゃない気がするの
How about I tie him up in a sack,
じゃあ私が麻袋で彼を縛って
beat him up,
それから殴って
and ask what he wants?
口を聞き出してみる？
Beating people up isn't a long-term solution.
それじゃ長い目で見れないわ
Isn't Butcher Guo the best example?
郭豚屠りが一番いい例じゃない？
Besides, booking a restaurant isn't illegal.
それに店を貸し切るのは 別に違法じゃないし
That makes sense.
それもそうね
Why is this clingy guy so annoying?
しつこくて本当にうっとうしい
I've seen enough of this domineering, big-spending act.
こんな金での駆け引きは見飽きたわ
If he really just likes me,
もし本当に私を好きなだけなら
and I want him to give up completely,
きっぱり諦めさせるには
I must sever his emotional attachment.
この想いを断ち切らせないと
I have to let him know
私には夫がいて
that I already have a husband,
もう隙がないってことを
so he doesn't stand a chance.
分からせるの
But you don't have a husband.
でも いないじゃない？
You do.
だけどあなたには夫がいるわ
I do, but you don't.
私にはいるわ でもあなたにはいないじゃない？